A Guide to the Margaret Grattan Weaver Collection 1753-1992
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Special Collections, James Madison University
Margaret Grattan Weaver Collection 1753-1992
Special Collections, James Madison University
2030
This collection consists of one Hollinger box and two oversize folders.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
A parchment land patent dated 31 May 1753 to Gabriel Jones, signed by Robt. Dinwiddie, was donated to Carrier Library by Mrs. Margaret Grattan Weaver of Harrisonburg in October, 1986. It was framed using preservation methods and materials and hangs on the south wall in the Special Collections Room (Room 205). The remainder of the collection, received in February 1992, is on deposit from the Harrisonburg-Rockingham Historical Society.
Biographical/Historical Information
John E. Roller, grandfather of Margaret G. Weaver, was born near Mt. Crawford in 1845, was a prominent lawyer, lecturer, and antiquarian in the Shenandoah Valley. He served in the Confederate Army, and in 1872 became major-general of the 3rd division of the Virginia militia. He also served as president of the Rockingham County Historical Society and pursued interests in local and religious history, amassing a considerable collection of books and papers.
Scope and Content
This collection contains a variety of documents relating to Mrs. Margaret G. Weaver and her ancestors, particularly her grandfather John E. Roller. Contained in this collection are a sampling of Roller's historical notes and speeches, some original documents relevant to local history, some Civil War materials, and a folder of genealogical data. A much larger collection of Roller family papers is located at the Virginia Historical Society in Richmond. The collection also contains genealogical information on the Grattan family, including a typescript of an autobiography (1849?) by Robert Grattan, and several essays by Margaret Grattan Weaver.
Arrangement
Series 1. John E. Roller Papers. Series 2. Biographical/Genealogical Information. Series 3. Civil War Documents (incl. 2 groups of pamphlets). Series 4. Oversize.
Contents List
- 1: John E. Rollers Papers (Box 1)
  - Letters (3 items) 1899, 1903, & undated (Folder 1)
  - Historical notes, writings, & speeches in typescript, carbon, photocopy & autograph 1886-1891 but mostly undated (Folder 2)
    Includes data on town of Mt. Pleasant, Rockingham Circuit, German Element in VA, John Lederer, Hebron Lutheran (Madison Cty.), Reformed Churches, Robert Patton, Cap. Conway, R'ham Cty. Hist. Soc, & one of Roller's legal cases.
  - Addresses. Typescripts, photocopies of printed programs, autograph drafts 1897-1910 (Folder 3)
    On Jeff Davis, Huguenots, Reformed Churches, Civil War.
  - Religious publications data undated (Folder 4)
    Notes on Roller's collection of catechisms; photocopies of exhibit & sale catalogs.
  - Original documents signed by Peter Roler, E. Roller, Samuel Shaklett, Robert & John Grattan & others in Rockingham Cty 1779-1900 & undated (Folder 5)
    Includes bonds for collection of taxes, road petitions and certifications, deed, & indictment for permitting an insane slave to go at large.
- 2: Biographical/Genealogical Information (Box 1)
  - Thomas Harrison House: copy of registration form for National Register of Historic Places 1990 (Folder 6)
  - Writings of M. G. Weaver, including "A history of Inglewood Farm and its people," essays on history and religion 1976-1992 & undated (Folder 7)
  - John E. Roller Biographical Data 1877-1990 (Folder 8)
    Includes genealogies, photocopies about JER, his 1918 obituary, and several invitations.
  - Grattan family data (Folder 9)
    Includes 37 p. typescript autobiography of Maj. Robert Grattan (1770-1849) with details about life and school in Harrisonburg area.
- 3: Civil War Documents (Box 1)
  - Original documents 1861-1870, 34 items (Folder 10)
    Mostly receipts for supplies in Richmond area; also monthly summary of funds, report on Richmond defences (June 1863 from H. Douglis to Col. Stevens), some personal notes concerning arms, transportation, & personnel; pieces of Merrimac and U.S. Cumberland.
  - Letters 1857-1894, 12 items (Folder 11)
    7 letters between J.C. Ingram & his mother; other misc. letters, incl. one 1894 from Mrs. Stonewall Jackson.
  - 11 pamphlets 1862-1980 & undated (Othertype Pam. Group 1)
    about the Civil War, incl. Battle of New Market, Southern & Confederate States almanacs, address by Gen. Early, a report by Maj.-Gen. Magruder, & Fredericksburg Battlefield map.
  - 18 pamphlets 1879-1893 (Othertype Pam. Group 2)
    annual addresses by Charles C. Jones Jr. to Confederate Survivors' Assn.
- 4: Oversize (Oversize Flat box 1)
  - Facsimile of land patent 1753 (Folder 1)
    to Gabriel Jones for 644 acres "on the north side of Shannando" in Augusta Cty. (now near Port Republic in Rockingham Cty.) signed by Rob(er)t Dinwiddie, Lieut. Gov. of VA. Original hanging on wall of Spec. Coll. room.
  - Misc. 1780 and undated (Folder 2)
    2 indentures signed 1780 by Peter Roler, 1 Latin document, one sheet with signatures pasted on both sides (incl. R.E.Lee & other military leaders), & 2 unidentified photos of female academy classes.
    These signatures were removed from their backing, deacidified, remounted with wheat paste on acid free backing, and encapsulated by Conservator Yolanda Warren in March 1993.
    - Side 1 (designated by the call no. label), First Row
      - J E. Johnston Lt. Gen
      - A.S. Johnston Genl CSA
      - W O Harvie Capt [A.C.S.,C.S.A., typed]
      - With great respect Yr. ot. servt A.S. Johnston Genl C.S.A
      - [illegible]
      - Frank Scott Maj G
      - D N Ingrahams Pay Officer [Commolly & C?]
      - L W Logan Brig Genl P.A.C.S
      - HEC Barker Capt ACS
    - Side 1, Second Row
      - S B [Thunkroger?] Chf army Rev
      - G E Pickett Capt C S Army
      - L. Polk Lt. Genl
      - T.J. Jackson Lieut Genl. C.S.A
      - T.J. Jackson Maj Genl
      - Yrs Brad T Johnson
    - Side 1, Third Row
      - Wm Procter Smith Col. Engineers C.S.A & Chief Eng. Army of N. Va during Gettysburg Campaign
      - Frank W Green Capt ACS
      - D.E. [Famys?] Ma[g?]er Genl C.S.A
      - Very truly yrs R.E. Withers
      - Bradley T. Johnson Brig. Genl
      - Wade Hampton Maj. Genl.
      - P.C. Hungerfords Capt. of Genl Smith's Division [A.C.S.,C.S.A., typed]
    - Side 2, First Row
      - John A. Seldon Capt. [A.C.S.,C.S.A., typed]
      - J. Richard Lewellen Maj Genl [Corndy?]
      - Very Respectfully, Genl, Your obt. Servt. Jos Wheeler Maj Genl.
      - R E Lee Genl
      - [I certify on honor that the above is a true report of all persons and articles employed, typed] R.G. Cole Lt Col
      - C G Memminger
      - Very Respectfully Yr Obt Sevt R.L. Walker Maj Genl [Corndy?] 3rd Comp Arty
      - Alexander N Stephens
      - Wm. W. [Narni?] Major [A.C.S.,C.S.A., typed]
    - Side 2, Second Row
      - LMMill
      - J H Claibourne Major ACS
    - Side 2, Third Row
      - [illegilbe] on August [illegible] Richmond 7 March 79
      - W. [M?] Smith Capt. & U.S.A. new General Superintendent of the C.S. Laboratory, Richmond, Va
      - J.P. Benjamin Secretary of War CSA
      - L P Walker Secty of War
      - [Brig?] W.M. [Thrician ?]
      - John Henry Wayt Capt [A.C.S.,C.S.A., typed]
      - J.D. Imboden Brig Genl Cavalry CSA
      - F M Boykin Lt. Col. 31st Va Infantry